<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve"
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The scientific evaluation of music content analysis systems: Valid empirical foundations for future real-world impact</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <licence/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename type="first">Bob</forename>
                                <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                                <surname>Sturm</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <email>b.sturm@qmul.ac.uk</email>
                            <affiliation key="aff0">
                                <orgName type="department">School of Electronic Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Mary University of London</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <region>Queen</region>
                                    <country key="GB">U.K</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename type="first">Hugo</forename>
                                <surname>Maruri-Aguilar</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <affiliation key="aff1">
                                <orgName type="department">School of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Mary University of London</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <region>Queen</region>
                                    <country key="GB">U.K</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename type="first">Ben</forename>
                                <surname>Parker</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <affiliation key="aff1">
                                <orgName type="department">School of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Mary University of London</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <region>Queen</region>
                                    <country key="GB">U.K</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <roleName>B.PARKER}@QMUL</roleName>
                                <forename type="first">{h</forename>
                                <forename type="middle">Ac</forename>
                                <surname>Maruri-Aguilar</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <affiliation key="aff1">
                                <orgName type="department">School of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Mary University of London</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <region>Queen</region>
                                    <country key="GB">U.K</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <surname>Uk</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <affiliation key="aff1">
                                <orgName type="department">School of Mathematical Sciences</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Mary University of London</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <region>Queen</region>
                                    <country key="GB">U.K</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename type="first">Heiko</forename>
                                <surname>Grossmann</surname>
                            </persName>
                            <email>heiko.grossmann@ovgu.de</email>
                            <affiliation key="aff2">
                                <orgName type="department">Institute for Mathematical Stochastics</orgName>
                                <orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke University</orgName>
                                <address>
                                    <settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
                                    <country key="DE">Germany</country>
                                </address>
                            </affiliation>
                        </author>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The scientific evaluation of music content analysis systems: Valid empirical foundations for future real-world impact</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <date/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <idno type="MD5">4D0B49B8C96222EF2B43CEE041F1ACCA</idno>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application version="0.7.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2023-02-11T07:45+0000">
                    <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
                    <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <abstract>
                <div
                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <p>We discuss the problem of music content analysis within the formal framework of experimental design.</p>
                </div>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <head n="1.">Preliminaries</head>
                <p>By the formalism developed in 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Sturm et al. (2014)</ref>, define a music universe Ω, a music recording universe R Ω , descriptor vocabularies F (features) and V (tokens), and Boolean semantic rules A : f → {T, F } and A : s → {T, F }, where f and s are finite sequences of elements in F and V, respectively. Define the semantic universe S V,A := {s ∈ V n |n ∈ N ∧ A(s) = T }.
                </p>
                <p>(1)</p>
                <p>The semantic feature universe S F,A is built similarly, using F and A . A recorded music description system S is a map</p>
                <formula xml:id="formula_0">S : R Ω → S V,A
                    <label>(2)</label>
                </formula>
                <p>which is a composition of two maps: E : R Ω → S F,A and C : S F,A → S V,A . The map E is commonly known as a "feature extractor," and C as a "classifier." A recorded music dataset is an indexed sample</p>
                <formula xml:id="formula_1">D = ((r i , s i ) : i ∈ I) ⊂ R Ω × S V,A
                    <label>(3)</label>
                </formula>
                <p>where I indexes the samples. The sequence (s i ) i∈I is called the ground truth of D. Finally, music content analysis research encompasses all aspects above in order to connect "users" (people, organisations, etc.) with music and information about music. </p>
            </div>
            <div
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <head n="2.">Experimental design in general</head>
                <p>Experimental design 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bailey, 2008)</ref> is necessary to plan, implement, analyse, and report valid tests of hypotheses while meeting constraints that are physical, economical, ethical, and so on. Fundamental concerns of experimental design are the specification of the treatments, the experimental and observational units (plots), the identification of structures in treatments and plots, the mapping of units to treatments, the relevance of the measurement, the modelling and analysis of measurements, and securing that an experiment can validly address given hypotheses.
                </p>
                <p>An experimental design maps plots {ω 1 , . . . , ω N } to treatments T = {1, . . . , t}, as represented by a design matrix</p>
                <formula xml:id="formula_2">X := [u 1 , • • • , u t ] N ×t , of N × 1 indicator vectors u i ,</formula>
                <p>where the jth row of u i is 1 if plot ω j receives treatment i, and 0 if not. Of interest are two subspaces: the treatment subspace V T := C(X), which is the column space of X, and its orthogonal complement V ⊥ T , which contains all N × 1 vectors orthogonal to X. Structure in the treatments and/or plots may prompt other decompositions of the space V = R N in order to test specific hypotheses.</p>
                <p>An experiment results in measurements on treated units, producing N responses y ∈ V . The effect of the treatments on y is often described by a linear model</p>
                <formula xml:id="formula_3">Y = τ + Z (4)</formula>
                <p>where τ = τ i u i ∈ V T and τ 1 , . . . , τ t are the treatment parameters (unknown constants). Moreover, Z is a random vector which can be modelled further to reflect structure in the plots and random error. Testing hypotheses about {τ i } relies upon assumptions about Z. The simple textbook model for unstructured plots and a completely randomised design assumes that Z ∼ N (0, σ 2 I N ). Structure in the plots necessitates the use of a different model for Z. Hypothesis testing by the method of analysis of variance de-composes y over orthogonal subspaces of V , such as V T and V ⊥ T , in accordance with the hypotheses and the plot structure, and then assesses their contributions.</p>
            </div>
            <div
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <head n="3.">Experimental design for MCA systems</head>
                <p>Of principal interest is a comparison of music content analysis (MCA) systems {S 1 , S 2 , . . .}, as in (2), which are the treatments T . A common experiment toward this proceeds: This is often done using K-fold cross validation (KfCV), or repeated random partitioning, in which case steps 2-4 are repeated. To summarise the results of this experiment, a figure of merit (FoM) is computed, e.g., accuracy, which is then used to make comparisons between treatments. This process is typified by the experiment of 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Tzanetakis &amp; Cook (2002)</ref>, which is one of the most cited articles in MCA. They use a D with 1000 recordings and a ground truth with 100 occurrences of each of the 10 elements (genre) in S V,A . They perform the experiment above with several systems using the same instance of E but different classifiers built from different methods. For each kind of system S k , they perform 100 repetitions of 10fCV in D. Each repetition uses a fresh random partition of the 100 recordings per genre in D into 10 mutually exclusive subsets A (j) 1 , . . . , A (j) 10 of size 10, where j = 1, . . . , 10 identifies the genre. For i = 1, . . . , 10 the ith fold is then defined as the set-theoretic union of A . Each 10fCV uses for each i ∈ {1, . . . , 10} the ith fold as I test and the union of the remaining nine folds as I train . For each (r i , s i ) ∈ D with i ∈ I test the response is 1 if the system output matches the ground truth, that is if S k (r i ) = s i , and 0 otherwise. This gives 1000 responses per repetition and a corresponding proportion of matches. Tzanetakis and Cook compute the mean rate of success (accuracy) and the standard deviation of those proportions over the 100 repetitions. The table below shows some of their results. Three conclusions they make from their experiment are:
                </p>
                <p>A. Since D is a "representative" sample from RΩ × SV,A, the FoM (based on D) of GS, GMM 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(3)</ref> and 
                    <ref type="bibr">KNN(3)</ref> in Table 
                    <ref type="table">3</ref> are "indicative" of the FoM that would be obtained if these kinds of systems were applied to the entire universe RΩ. B. Since the FoM of GS, GMM(3) and KNN(3) using the proposed E are better than randomly mapping RΩ to SV,A (in which case the FoM is expected to be 0.10), the set S F,A is informative for SV,A in the whole universe RΩ. C. Since the FoM in Table 
                    <ref type="table">3</ref> are better than randomly mapping RΩ to SV,A, the systems are recognising SV,A in RΩ.
                </p>
                <p>The validity of each of these conclusions relies on two strong assumptions. Conclusion A assumes that D is a random sample from R Ω × S V,A , a set that is never explicitly defined. Since there is clear evidence that D is not a random sample 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Sturm, 2014)</ref>, the experiment may or may not result in FoM that reflect the performance of a system applied to R Ω . The other two conclusions relate to the behaviour expected of a system operating randomly, and assume that an MCA system's ability to reproduce the ground truth of D is either due to chance or caused by "musical content" relating R Ω to S V,A . This assumption is not true: another way to reproduce the ground truth of D is by exploiting "non-musical content" (characteristics of subsets of R Ω unrelated to S V,A ), e.g., a confounding introduced by the construction of D. The existence of such confounding in the dataset used in 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Tzanetakis &amp; Cook (2002)</ref>, as well as others, has been clearly demonstrated 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Pampalk et al., 2005;</ref>
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sturm, 2014)</ref>. Because of its lack of control over such a possibility, the experiment above has no validity for conclusions B and C.
                </p>
                <p>A possible measurement model for the experiment in line with 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bailey (2008)</ref> would recognise the individual cross validations as the observational units and "repetitions" as an additional plot factor. A system of each kind k is applied as a treatment to 100 whole repetitions (each consisting of 10 units). The response for each unit u is the proportion of correct classifications of the 100 pairs (r i , s i ) with i ∈ I test (u, v), where I test (u, v) denotes the test set for the validation u in repetition v. Denote by p kuv the probability that a system of type k gives a correct classification for u and v. A model for this situation is
                </p>
                <formula xml:id="formula_4">p kuv = β 0 + β k + γ v + uv ,
                    <label>(5)</label>
                </formula>
                <p>where, using an appropriate parameterisation, β 0 is the probability of success of a random system and β k is the additional contribution of the system to type k. Further, γ v is a contribution due to the random partitioning in repetition v, and uv models all other "errors" independent of the system type due to cross validation instances u within v. For this interpretation of β 0 and β k to be valid, the experiment would also need to include a random system.</p>
                <p>To provide evidence for the conclusions B and C of 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Tzanetakis &amp; Cook (2002)</ref> one would need to test the hypothesis β k = 0 in (5). This test would then be performed in the stratum for repetitions. For three kinds of systems, as in the table above, and an additional random system (each with 100 repetitions and 10 validations) and assuming normality, the corresponding F test has 396 denominator degrees of freedom. Assuming all individual cross validations are independent can result in an incorrect test overstating the significance of the results. The applicability of this is suspect, however, since γ v is known to depend on the system type 
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Pampalk et al., 2005;</ref>
                    <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Sturm, 2014)</ref>.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="references">
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b0">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m" type="main">Build or choose a D, indexed by I 2. Partition I into non-overlapping sets Itrain</title>
                            <imprint/>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Itest</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b1">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m" type="main">} from tuples of D indexed by Itrain 4. Treat recordings of D indexed by Itest and compare results to ground truth</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <surname>Build</surname>
                                    <genName>{S1</genName>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">.</forename>
                                    <surname>S2</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <imprint/>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>record successes and failures</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b2">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m" type="main">Design of comparative experiments</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">R</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                                    <surname>Bailey</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <imprint>
                                <date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b3">
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">Improvements of audiobased music similarity and genre classification</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">E</forename>
                                    <surname>Pampalk</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">A</forename>
                                    <surname>Flexer</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">G</forename>
                                    <surname>Widmer</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proc. IS-MIR</title>
                            <meeting>IS-MIR</meeting>
                            <imprint>
                                <date type="published" when="2005-09">Sep. 2005</date>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="233" />
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b4">
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">The state of the art ten years after a state of the art: Future research in music information retrieval</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">B</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                                    <surname>Sturm</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">J. New Music Research</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="172" />
                                <date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b5">
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">Formalizing the problem of music description</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">B</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                                    <surname>Sturm</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">R</forename>
                                    <surname>Bardeli</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">T</forename>
                                    <surname>Langlois</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">V</forename>
                                    <surname>Emiya</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ISMIR</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="94" />
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="b6">
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">Musical genre classification of audio signals</title>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">G</forename>
                                    <surname>Tzanetakis</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <persName>
                                    <forename type="first">P</forename>
                                    <surname>Cook</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Speech Audio Process</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="302" />
                                <date type="published" when="2002-07">July 2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>